字幕转制｜天外生物
感谢原字幕制作者
我是布莱克
早上好 布莱克先生 我是阿曼达
Good morning, Mr Blake. My name's Amanda.
今天我想问您几个问题
I've got a couple of questions here for you today
以评估您是否有获得就业支持津贴的资格
to establish your eligibility for Employment Support Allowance.
不会占用您太多时间
It won't take up much of your time.
首先 我想请问
Could I just ask firstly,
您是否能独自行走五十米以上
can you walk more than 50 metres unassisted by any other person?
- 能  - 好的
- Yes.  - Okay.
您是否能举起两边手臂 就像将物品放入上衣口袋的动作
Can you raise either arm as if to put something in your top pocket?
这我已经在你们五十二页的表格里填过了
I've filled this in already on your 52-page form.
是的 您已经填写过了
Yeah, I can see that you have
但不好意思 您的答案并不明确
but, unfortunately, I couldn't make out what you had said there.
可以
Yes.
您是否能把双臂举过头顶
Can you raise either arm to the top of your head
就像戴上帽子的动作
as if you are putting on a hat?
我说过了 我的手和脚没有毛病
I've telt you, there's nowt wrong with me arms and legs.
请您直接回答问题 好吗
Could you just answer the question, please.
你明明有我的医疗记录
Well, you've got me medical records.
能不能就谈我的心脏问题
Can we just talk about me heart?
请您直接回答问题 好吗
D'you think you could just answer these questions?
好吧
Okay.
所以您是可以自己戴上帽子吗
So was that a yes, that you can put a hat on your head?
- 可以  - 好的
- Yes.  - Okay, that's great.
您按键是否有困难 比如电话拨号
Can you press a button such as a telephone keypad?
我手指也没毛病啊
There's nowt wrong with me fingers either.
怎么离我的心脏越来越远了
I mean, we're getting farther and farther away from me heart.
请您回答问题 谢谢配合
If we could just keep to these questions, thank you.
您在向陌生人传达简单信息时
Do you have any significant difficulty
是否有较大的困难？
conveying a simple message to strangers?
有 我反复跟你说我的心脏问题 可你就是不听啊
Yes. Yes, it's me fucking heart. I 'm trying to tell you but you'll not listen.
布莱克先生 如果您再使用这种语气
Mr Blake, if you continue to speak to us like that
会直接影响您的评估结果
that's not gonna be very helpful for your assessment.
请您直接回答问题
If you could just answer the question, please.
- 好吧  - 好的
- Yes.  - Okay.
您是否曾出现过严重排便失禁情况
Do you ever experience any loss of control leading to extensive evacuation of the bowel?
没有 但咱要再这么兜圈子
No. But I cannot guarantee
我就真要失禁了
there won't be a first if we divvent get to the point.
您是否可以独立设置闹钟
Can you complete a simple task of setting an alarm clock?
上帝啊 当然可以
Oh, Jesus. Yes.
能问你个问题吗 你有行医资格吗
Can I ask you a question? Are you medically qualified?
我是由政府就业和养老金部
I'm a health care professional
指派的医保专业人员
appointed by the Department of Work and Pensions
负责审核就业支持津贴的获取资格
to carry out assessments for Employment and Support Allowance.
但刚才等候室里有个哥们
But there was a bloke out in the, er, in the waiting room,
他说你们其实是一家美国公司
he says that you work for an American company.
我们公司是政府官方授权的
Our company's been appointed by the Government.
你是护士吗 还是医生
Are you a nurse? Are you a doctor?
我是一名医保专业人员
I'm a health care professional.
听着 我犯过一次严重的心脏病
Listen, I've had a major heart attack.
差点从施工架上摔下来
I nearly fell off the scaffolding.
我也想赶紧回到工作岗位
I wanna get back to work, too.
行行好 能不能谈谈我的心脏
Now, please, can we talk about me heart?
别老纠结我的屁股 我排便通畅得很
Forget about me arse, that works a dream.
派普 你个懒鬼
Piper, you lazy bastard.
赶紧起床干点家务
Will you get out of bed and do some housework!
老中
China!
不好意思 丹 我刚收到工作短信 要迟到了
Sorry, Dan, just got a text to go to work. I'm late.
玛莎拉咖喱鸡块好吃吗
Did you enjoy your chicken tikka masala?
- 你怎么知道  - 这味儿直往我鼻子里窜
- How did you know that?  - Cos I can bloody smell it.
我说过多少次了不要把垃圾留在门口
How many times have I told you about leaving rubbish lying about the place,
臭烘烘的
stinking it up?
- 我待会倒行吗 要迟到了  - 不行 现在就倒
- Can I dump it later? I'm running late.  - No. Now!
丹…
Dan...
我想请你帮个忙
Erm, I've got a big favour to ask
我在等一个很重要的包裹
I'm expecting a package. Really important.
我调班了 收件时我不会在家
They've changed my hours, so I won't be in.
你能帮我留意一下快递员吗
Can you keep an eye out for the postman?
除非你发誓 不再乱放垃圾
If you swear nae more rubbish.
- 接住  - 你小子敢
- Catch!  - Don't you fucking dare.
- 我一脚把你踹到外太空  - 行行
- I'll kick your arse into next week.  - Okay.
介倒霉孩子
Daft as a bloody brush.
我什么时候能回去工作
When can I go back to work?
现在肯定不行
Ah, not yet, that's for certain.
但你正在恢复
You're making progress.
要保持相同的药量
I think if we just continue you on the same dosage.
继续做复健练习
And, yeah, rehab exercise.
看能不能提高心脏的供血能力
We'll see if we can the pumping capacity to increase.
- 好  - 很可能会哦
- Yeah.  - And it might.
如果没有 就要装一个心脏除颤器
But if not, we might need to look at fitting you with a defibrillator.
坚持锻炼和走动 会恢复得更快
Keep up with the exercise, keep moving. That's gonna build you up.
同时也需要多休息
But you need to be rested as well.
我可是个夜猫子呢
Well, I'm a bit of a night owl, you know.
以前照顾老婆时养成的习惯
I got into the habit when I was looking after the missus
在她去世以前
before she passed away.
最近怎么样
How you doing, son? How you doing?
- 还行吧  - 心脏挺得住吧
- All right.  - How's the old ticker?
壮年一去不复返啊
Ah, you know, me marathon days are over.
没事 一两个月就能康复了
But, you know, I'll be fine in a month or two.
别碰壮阳药啊
Ah, well, be leaving that Viagra alone.
我全给你留着呢
I'll keep it for you, shall I?
是啊 反正你也用不上
Aye, I probably need it more than you.
有没有想拿走的东西
Right, well, owt you want here?
- 你看看  - 这块不错
- Have a look  - Oh, that's nice, aye.
梅兰蒂木 正宗的非洲梅兰蒂木 好得很
Meranti, aye, African Meranti. It's great, man.
你还会回弗格森的公司吗
So, er, d'you reckon you'll get back to Ferguson's?
看有没有活干吧
Depends on the work, I suppose.
你也知道 最近不太景气
I mean, you know what it's like. It's up and down.
是啊
Aye, well.
你一定要看看这个
Gotta see this.
就是这个
There you go.
这活儿做得讲究啊
Oh, that's a lovely piece.
我叫手下的人给你带一块过去
Aye, I'll have the... I'll have the lads drop it by for you.
你身体没事吧
Erm, are you all right?
在恢复了
I'm on the mend.
买东西的事交给我吧
I mean, I can get your shopping sorted out for you, you know.
帮你拎点重东西 举手之劳
Like, the heavy stuff and that, like, it's nae bother.
谢了乔 我还是想多活动活动
Thanks, Joe. You know, I like to get out and about.
至少不闲着
Gives us something to do.
有困难就说话
Well, give us a shout if you need anything.
我说真的
I mean, I mean that.
你可真把我们吓得不轻
You, you gave us a big fright, you know.
BBC电台四频道 现在时间十二点四十八分
BBC Radio Four, it's twelve minutes to 1:00.
气象局代表海事和海岸警卫队
Now the shipping forecast, issued by the Met Office
现在播送海域天气预报
on behalf of the Maritime and Coastguard Agency
气象发布时间十月二十日星期二 零点十五分
at double-O-1-5 on Tuesday the 20th of October.
在特拉法格有大风预警…
There are warnings of gales in Trafalgar, Fitzroy...
请注意 本次通话可能会收取费用
Please be aware that this call may incur a charge.
您的通话费将由本人的电话公司收取
You will be charged at the rate set by your service provider.
本号仅用于已有福利申请查询
This number is for benefits enquiries only.
如果您是为了新的福利申请而致电 请重新拨打号码
If you are calling to make a new claim for benefits, please redial,
〇八〇〇 〇五五 六八八八
0800-055-6888
那样会尽快收到申请回复
to help answer your query as quickly as possible.
很抱歉 客服全部占线中
We are sorry, but all our customer service agents are busy at the moment.
请勿挂机 我们会尽快接听
Please hold and we will answer your call.
哎 你那捣鼓什么呢
Oi! What are ye playing at?
我就知道是你 让自家狗到处拉屎是吧
I knew it was ye! I knew it was ye letting your dog shit round here.
我就是遛个狗嘛
I'm walking me dog.
我就知道是你 带条狗来拉得满处都是
I knew it was you bringing your dog in here, shitting all over the place.
闭嘴吧 死秃子
Oh shut your mouth, you stupid baldy bastard.
小心我下去把你脸怼到屎堆里
Oi! Ye, if I come down there, I'll rub your bloody face in it, man!
要拉回你自己家拉去
Take it to your own place and let it shit round there.
- 去找个袋子捡起来  - 哦
- Go and get a bag and clean that up.  - Aye, I'm gonna get a bag
少废话
I tell you what, ye talk shite!
快点找个袋子
Here, look, you just get a bag!
- 把狗屎清了再走  - 闭嘴吧
- Come back here and bloody clean that up.  - Oh, shut up, man, will you!
我去你家花园拉个屎行不行
Hey! I'll come and shite in your garden, shall I?
闭嘴吧
Shut up.
喂
Hello?
感谢您的耐心等待
Thank you for waiting.
请不要挂机 我们会尽快接听您的电话
Please continue to hold and we will answer your call as soon as possible.
你好 这是马科斯·米利安的包裹
Morning, mate. Got a package for Mr Max Million.
- 马科斯·米利安？ - 对 就是他
- "Mr Max Million"?  - Yeah. Mr Max Million.
送到我家的？
My address?
地址没错
Yeah, definitely this address.
- 从哪寄来的  - 中国
- Where's it from?  - China.
拿进来吧
Oh. Give it here.
你知道我等了多久吗
D'you know how long I've been on this phone?
一小时四十八分钟
One hour, forty-eight minutes.
老天 比一场足球赛还长 电话费要上天了
Jesus Christ, that's longer than a football match. It'll cost a fortune.
很抱歉 先生 我们今天很忙
I'm sorry, sir, but it's been very busy.
肯定是哪里搞错了吧
There must be some mistake.
我有很严重的心脏病
I've got a serious heart condition.
我正在休养 医生不让我回去工作
I'm in rehab and the doctor's told us I cannae go back to work.
本来还能领福利 现在又搞什么评估
Now, I was getting the benefits fine until that bloody assessment.
您的评估只获得了十二分
I see you've only scored twelve points, er,
您需要十五分才能继续领取福利
and you need 15 to obtain benefits.
什么分数 你们花样够多的
Oh, points, that's your game?
抱歉先生 据医保…
I'm sorry, sir, but according to our health, er,
医保专业人员的记录
health care professional,
您目前尚有工作能力
you've been deemed fit for work.
这么说她比我的外科顾问医生
So she knows better than my doctor,
和专业理疗团队还厉害？
a consultant surgeon and a physio team?
我要申诉
Well, I wanna appeal.
可以
Well, that's fine,
但您要先申请“强制再评估”
but you'll have to first request a mandatory reconsideration.
这他妈又是什么意思
What the bloody hell does that mean?
意思是 决策者会重新考虑您的申请
It means the decision maker will reconsider it
如果依然驳回 您才能开始申诉
and if he comes to the same decision, you can then appeal.
行 那我就再评估吧
Right, well put us down for that, then.
可以 但您要先等
Okay, sir, but you must wait
决策者给您打电话
to get a call from the decision maker.
为什么
Why?
告诉您他们再次考虑的结果
To tell you what the decision is.
不是已经出结果了吗
But that's already been decided.
是 但在收到信函之前
It is, but you're supposed to get the call,
他们会先打电话给您
before the letter.
他们还会改变主意不成
Well, is he gonna change his mind?
不 电话内容就是讨论评估结果
No, the call's just to discuss the decision.
结果我知道啊 信函就放在我面前呢
Well, I know what the decision is, I've got the letter here in front of us.
不然我读给你听听
D'you want us to read it to you?
收信前应该接到电话才对啊
But he should have called you first.
可他没打啊
But he didn't.
但他应该打啊
But he should have.
除非穿越回去 否则咱是扯不清了
Well unless we've got a time machine, we're pretty much knackered,
对吧
divvent you agree?
您必须先接到决策者的电话 先生
Er, he has to call you first, sir.
听着
Listen,
让他现在接电话吧 别再浪费时间了
can you not just put him on now, so I don't have to waste any more time?
这不行 先生
I can't do that, sir.
他人在哪
Where is he?
他一有时间就会
He'll give you a call back when he, er,
- 给您电话的  - 什么时候
- he gets the chance.  - When?
我也不知道 先生
I don't know, sir.
真是邪了门了
This is ridiculous, man.
一方面 失业津贴只发放
On the one hand, Jobseeker's Allowance,
给有工作能力的人
only for those able and ready to work.
如果您有疾病 就只能申请就业支持津贴
But if you're ill, you have to apply for Employment and Support,
并通过相关评估
get an assessment carried out.
我评估过了 但被驳回了
Well, I've done that but they've knocked us back.
如果您被判定具备工作能力
Right, well if you've been deemed fit for work,
您就只能申请失业津贴
your only option is Jobseeker's Allowance.
或进行就业支持津贴的申诉
Or proceed with the appeal on Employment and Support.
你能给我张…
Well, can you give me a form for...
失业津贴 和
You know, erm, Jobseeker's Allowance
就业支持津贴的申诉表格吗
and then an appeal form Employment and Support?
表格需要在网上填写
You have to apply online, sir.
我不会上网啊
I cannot do that.
没办法先生 您也可以拨打求助热线
Well that's how it is, sir. Or you can phone the helpline.
要是给我张图纸
Listen, you know, you give me a plot of land,
我分分钟就能盖房子
I can build you a house.
可我这辈子都没碰过电脑
But I've never been anywhere near a computer.
我们是默认数字化系统
D'you know what, we're digital by default.
又来了
Oh, here we gan.
“默认数字化” 电话上都听烦了
I hear this all the time on the phone, "I'm digital by default."
我还“默认铅笔化”呢
Well I'm pencil by default.
那些不会上网的人怎么办
Look, I mean, what happens if you just cannae do it?
如果您有阅读障碍 我们有专属热线
There's a special number if you've been diagnosed as dyslexic.
行啊 反正我在电脑上就是个文盲
Right, well can you give us that? Cos with computers I'm dyslexic.
该选项可以在网页上找到 如果您没有预约
You'll find it online, sir. I must ask you to leave now,
我得请您离开了
if you've got no appointment.
你有事吗
Right, can I help you?
我来是想换掉现在的工作指导
Yeah, I'm here to see about changing my work coach.
托马斯·阿姆斯特朗
Thomas Armstrong, please.
请等一下 托马斯
Hang on a minute, Thomas, hang on.
您需要坐一下吗
Erm, would you like to take a seat?
我缓一缓就好 突然有点头晕
Oh, I just need a minute. I just felt... I'm just feeling dizzy, you know.
- 来坐会吧  - 谢谢
- Come and sit down.  - Oh, cheers, thanks.
能挪一下吗
Could you move up, please, love?
多谢了
Thanks, pet, thank you.
- 好了 我给您拿杯水吧  - 谢谢
- All right. I'll just get you a glass of water.  - Thank you.
谢谢
Oh, thank you, pet. Thank you.
没事吧 看您脸色不太好
Are you all right? You look a bit pale.
这些术语 都把我搞晕了
It's just so bloody confusing, all the jargon.
肯定是哪搞错了 我一直在兜圈子
I mean, there must be some mistake. I'm just ganning round and round in circles.
我今天真的需要把事情办好
I've, I've really gotta get this sorted out.
这我明白 但你确实来晚了
Oh I can understand that, but you were late.
托马斯 您喝点水休息一下吧
Thomas. You sit here and drink your water, pet.
谢谢
Thank you.
现在你要处罚我了…
So now you're gonna sanction me so, er...
- 我不是要处罚你  - 我可能会一个月拿不到钱啊
- No, I'm not gonna sanction you.  - I may not get any money for a month.
我会把你的情况上报给决策者 他们会做最终裁决
I'm gonna refer you to the decision maker and they'll make the decision
- 看是否进行处罚  - 不可理喻…
- on whether they're gonna sanction you.  - That's ridiculous...
我无权决定 他们才有
I'm not actually making the decision, they're gonna do that.
如果决定处罚
And then if they do decide to sanction you,
福利会削减百分之四十
then you will take a 40% cut in your benefits.
我知道 你不用再科普了
I know what it is, I don't need you to explain it to me.
- 我清楚得很…  - 今天就这样
- I'm more than aware...  - Well there isn't anything else
也只能先到这为止了
anybody can do today.
那我现在只能…
So what I'm gonna have to do is, look, I think I'm...
我只能… 你真的要把我提交处罚？
I've decided to... Are you gonna put me in for a sanction?
没办法 要遵守规定
I have to, I have to follow the rules.
如果您态度再这么恶劣
And the thing is if you're gonna, be aggressive with me
- 我就必须要求…  - 我态度恶劣根本不是重点
- then I'm gonna have to ask you...  - It's not about me being aggressive.
- 我就必须要求您离开了  - 我只是在说明情况
- I'm gonna have to ask you to leave.  - I'm trying to explain to you a situation
你却毫不关心
and you don't care.
- 保安 保安呢  - 你根本不配做这份工作
- Er, security. Security?  - I don't know why people like you do this job.
我会上报给决策者的
I'm referring you to the decision maker.
还不是一样的结果 你这样说话我不想听
It's all the same thing. I don't wanna hear your language
- 你说什么  - 不好意思
- I, I beg your pardon.  - Listen, I, I'm sorry, love,
- 请您离开  - 行啊 反正很显然
- but you're gonna have to leave.  - Yeah, all right, frankly,
你别碰我 我要找你们经理
take your hands off me. I'm gonna speak to the manager,
- 不想跟你再谈了  - 我只是在解释情况…
- I don't wanna speak to you.  - The fact is I'm just trying to explain...
- 什么？ - 我只是在解释…
- Sorry?  - I'm just explaining...
没你事儿了…
Well it's not you I wanna speak to...
- 你回去吧  - 跟我说吧
- You can go back up there.  - Right, come and talk to me then
- 如果你确实需要解释  - 对不起
- if you've got something to say.  - Okay. Sorry.
好 是这样的
All right.
我刚才跟她解释说 我从没来过纽卡斯尔
I've tried to explain to the woman, I've never been to Newcastle before.
我们刚从伦敦搬来
We've just moved up here from London.
才几天时间 人生地不熟的
I've been here a few days, I don't know where I'm going. Okay?
刚才搭公车 开错了路
I was on the bus, it's gone the wrong way.
我们赶紧下车一路跑过来 不想再迟更多
We've run, got off the bus, run so that I wasn't any more late.
但她根本不关心
She just don't wanna know
还要上报上级处罚我们
and now she's telling me she's gonna refer me for a sanction.
请您听我说 好吗
What I want you to do is listen to me. Okay?
那位女士没有错
The lady's told you what's right.
我们必须遵守相关规定
There's rules here, rules that we have to stick to. Okay?
- 这不是针对您本人 但您有义务准时到达  - 老兄 听着
- It isn't against you, but you have a duty.  - Oh, mate, listen,
- 我没说你们针对我  - 您有义务准时到达
- I'm not saying it's against me.  - You have a duty to be here on time.
我有给你们解释
And I'm explaining to you
迟到的原因啊
why I wasn't here on time.
- 这我明白…  - 我迷路了
- D'you know what? I understand, right...  - I got lost.
但现在的情况是…
But what I gather now is the decision maker...
决策者会邮寄给您一封信函
The decision maker's gonna be sending you a letter through the post.
请您耐心等待
So you're gonna have to wait for that.
- 这样就不会有人…  - 可是我的孩子们
- And then nobody...  - Yeah, I've got... My kids
明天就开学了 我口袋里只剩十二英镑
have gotta start school tomorrow. I've got about 12 quid in my purse.
- 是这样  - 都是因为你们不好好冷静点
- D'you know what?  - All because you can't just calm down
- 听人们解释  - 好吧
- and listen to people when they talk.  - Right.
- 现在必须这样  - 好吧 这样
- You have to do this.  - Right, d'you know what,
- 我听了您的解释 可您在无理取闹  - 就知道搬规定
- I've listened to you. You've created a scene.  - With your rules.
- 我觉得…  - 我无理取闹？
- I think you need to...  - I've created a scene?
- 请您离开  - 我要真无理取闹
- You need to leave the building.  - If I was gonna create a scene,
你可招架不住
you'd know about it, trust me.
对不起 请你们离开
I'm sorry, love, but you are gonna have to go.
太可笑了
This is ridiculous.
- 还有天理吗  - 我该怎么办
- Jesus Christ!  - What am I supposed to do?
- 谁是下一个  - 我
- Who's first in this queue?  - I am.
能让这位小姐插个队吗
D'you mind if this young lass signs on first?
- 没问题 你们先  - 得嘞
- No, no, you carry on.  - There you go.
你回去 让她登记
Now you can go back to your desk and let her sign on
别再浪费纳税人的钱了
and do the job that the taxpayer pays you for.
- 简直是丢人现眼  - 您瞧
- This is a bloody disgrace.  - Listen, all right,
这不关您的事吧
this doesn't have to involve you.
大家各司其职 您却更加无理取闹
Everybody's trying to do their job here and you're creating more of a scene again.
你根本不听她解释
But, look, you're not listening to her.
她初来乍到的 就迟到了几分钟…
She's out of the area. She's just been a few minutes...
你这就不让她登记？她还带着俩孩子呢
Can you not let her sign on? She's got two kids with her, man.
- 你们这群人到底怎么回事  - 这不关您的事
- What's wrong with you people?  - Right, listen, this isn't your concern.
请您也立即离开
I want you to get out as well. All right?
请您离开 我们有工作要做
I need you to leave. We need to do this right. Yeah.
- 行吧  - 听我说…
- All right.  - Listen, listen, listen...
- 他们可会直接报警了  - 报警
- They're just gonna call the police.  - Phone the police.
能不能讲点道理 还有没有王法
Can we get some perspective in here?
请你们立即离开 否则我们报警了
You need to go or we're gonna phone the police. All right?
我谢谢您啊
Come on. Thanks very much...
讲点道理吧
Can we have a bit of perspective, please, here, man?
- 别再继续犯傻了  - 你根本不配做这工作
- Away, don't be silly.  - Shouldn't even have this job.
- 快走吧  - 你根本不配做这工作
- Come on. Please.  - Shouldn't even have this job.
- 快走  - 她只是需要帮助
- Come on, get out.  - All she needs is help, man.
- 快走 好吗  - 让她登个记怎么了
- Let's get going.  - Just let her sign on.
快走吧
Let's get going, all right.
拜托
Please.
你们这些人怎么回事我真是不明白了
I don't know what's wrong with you lot, I really don't.
往外走 不要停
I need you to keep going for me, okay?
- 我来拎一个吧  - 没事 不要紧
- You want me to take one of them bags?  - No, it's all right, I'm fine, pet. I'm fine.
- 迪伦呢  - 我不知道
- Where's Dylan?  - I don't know.
迪伦 快跟上
Dylan! Come on!
- 人呢  - 他可真是个小捣蛋
- Honestly. Honestly.  - He's a handful, isn't he?
这孩子连五分钟都不让人安生
I can't sit down for five minutes without him getting in trouble, can I?
是啊
Right.
- 选得好  - 她喜欢吃意面
- Good, good choice.  - She loves spaghetti.
意面配面包怎么做都好吃
Hey, you cannae go wrong with spaghetti on toast.
单吃或者配面包都好吃
Spaghetti, spaghetti on toast, isn't it?
你弟弟又跑哪了
Where's your brother gone?
- 迪伦  - 迪伦
- Dylan!  - Dylan!
快跟上
Come on.
他总是一溜烟就不见了
This, this is what he does. He runs, he runs off.
- 真是个捣蛋鬼  - 快跟上
- He's a handful, in't he?  - Come on!
你是去探险了吗
Where ye been, on an adventure?
迪伦 别蹭篱笆
Dylan, not on the fences.
- 就这里  - 妈妈 看 狗狗回来了
- It's just here.  - Mum, look, she's back, she's back.
她回来了
She's back.
如果只剩一件事可做 我会把这房子收拾得像个家
Tell you what, if it's the last thing I do, I'm gonna make this place a home.
你会修水箱吗
You don't know how to fix a cistern, do you?
快把我逼疯了
It's driving me insane.
- 我帮你看看吧  - 真的？
- Yeah, I'll have a look at that.  - Yeah?
我什么都会修
I can fix owt, me, pet,
除了电脑
apart from computers.
- 就在楼上 你带他…  - 我带他去吧
- Straight up. You show him...  - I'll show him.
迪伦 别闹了好不好 进屋
Dylan, can you stop it? Get in.
妈妈 你好吗
Hello, Mum. How are you doing?
对
Yeah.
对 都挺好的
Yeah, all right. All right. Yeah.
挺漂亮的 还很宽敞
It's nice, it's nice. There's plenty of space.
楼下有张很舒服的地毯
And, erm, yeah, it looks like they've put... There's a nice bit of fresh carpet down.
墙面刷得也很好
The, the walls are all nicely painted and that.
我知道 妈妈 等你身体好点 我们也安顿好了
No, I know, Mum. Well, look, once... Once you're feeling better and we're settled,
你就跟梅姨妈一起来住 好吗
then you'll have to come up. You can come up with Auntie May and stay, can't you?
这里人很好 比伦敦人友善
Yeah, they're nice, yeah, friendly. Friendlier than London.
是啊
Yeah.
你想跟黛西说说话吗
D'you wanna have a word with Daisy?
好 等一下 是外婆
All right, hold on. Talk to Nana.
喂 外婆
Hello, Nan.
- 黛西 你还好吗  - 挺好的
- Hello, Daisy. How are you?  - Good.
- 是吗 新家你喜欢吗  - 喜欢
- Yeah? D'you like it?  - Yeah.
- 在那里还开心吗  - 很开心
- Are you happy?  - Yeah, very.
我也想你 外婆再见
I miss you, too. Bye.
再见
Bye-bye.
喂 妈
Hello, Mum.
好 没关系 不要紧 我会去…
All right. That's all right. All right, I'll speak... Yeah, I've gotta go
我会去说的 明天再打给你
but I'll speak, I'll call you tomorrow.
- 好  - 好了 爱你
- All right.  - All right, love you.
- 我也爱你 再见  - 再见
- Love you, too. Bye.  - Bye, bye, bye.
你们为什么从伦敦搬过来 凯蒂
So what are you doing up here, Katie?
起先是因为我们被房东赶出来了
It started when we got kicked out of the flat.
因为一点小事
We got in a bit of trouble.
简直太冤枉了
It was ridiculous.
迪伦房间的墙壁漏水
In Dylan's room there was a leak coming through the wall,
从天花板渗到墙里的
coming through the top of the ceiling down the wall.
他就生病了 记得吗
And it was making him really sick. Weren't it, Dais?
- 记得迪伦那时候生病吗  - 记得
- Remember when Dylan weren't well?  - Yeah.
大老远跑去医院
We had to run all the way to the hospital.
去了好几次医院
Yeah, he was in and out the hospital.
我就去找房东
I was talking to the landlord about it, spoke to him.
抱怨了两句 就被赶出来了
And cos I complained, kicked us out.
什么 他们居然能这样
What, they can just do that?
- 随便赶人  - 是啊
- Just throw you out?  - Yeah, yeah.
所以我们就搬了出去
So we got out of there.
之后我们在临时救济房住了两年 等着政府的福利房
We was in a homeless hostel for about two years, waiting on a flat.
那离学校很近 他们很喜欢那所学校…
Yeah. But it was close to their school which they loved, so...
我们就只能忍着了 但只有一个房间
We just had to stick it out. But we was in one room,
三个人一起住一间房
the three of us were in one room.
吃饭睡觉都挤在一个房间里 迪伦都开始爬墙了
Like eating, sleeping, all the rest of it and Dylan was just climbing the walls.
真的像是闷在盒子里
Honestly, like boxed in like that, so, yeah.
最后 终于等到了新的福利房 好消息是 终于真的算是房子了
They eventually offered me a flat, so the good news was it was a flat.
坏消息是 地点在纽卡斯尔
Bad news was it was up here.
他们不能分给离你家人近一点的房子吗
And they couldn't give you anywhere near your family?
伦敦没有
No, not in London.
穷人在伦敦没法生活 成本太高了
They're, they're moving out the likes of me. It's just too expensive for 'em.
孩子们能适应吗
So how's the kids taking it?
转学可让他们伤心死了
They're brokenhearted about leaving school.
特别是黛西 她可怨我了
Especially Daisy. She's furious with me.
与朋友和外婆分别
Having to leave her friends and her nan.
可我有什么办法呢 总不能让迪伦憋在盒子里
I mean there was nothing I could do about it. I couldn't have Dylan boxed in like that.
- 交新朋友很快的  - 我也是这么说的
- Ah, she'll make friends soon enough.  - That's what I've told her.
我都规划好了
And I've got a plan.
外面有个小花园 每个人都有自己的房间
We got a little garden now and they've each got a room of their own.
我会找个兼职 然后继续念书
I'm gonna get a part-time job and then I'm gonna go back to me books.
- 你还是大学生？ - 是开放大学
- Oh, you at college?  - Open University.
我以前成绩不好 就当重新来过吧
Yeah, I mucked up a little bit at school so it's like a second chance.
住进临时救济房后 学业就中断了
But that all fell apart a little bit when we was at the hostel,
但我不能放弃
but I'm not gonna give up.
对吧
Can't, can I?
好样的 姑娘
Good on you, lass.
这屋里好冷啊
It's bloody freezing in here.
肯定是跳闸了
Oh, it must be a short.
你家的电闸在哪
Right, where's your fuse box?
电表里没钱了
There's nothing on the metre.
要开学了 我想给他们买点新衣服
The kids are starting school and I wanted to get 'em some nice new clothes.
以为明天就能领到救济
And I thought I was gonna get me money tomorrow.
好
Right.
我去拿工具箱 今天就帮你安顿好
I'll bring me tools round and I'll sort this place out for you.
- 真的吗  - 当然啦
- Will ya?  - Yeah, course I will.
很快就能修好
Shouldn't take long.
好 谢谢你
Right, thank you.
“马科斯·米利安”？ 还敢寄到我家
"Max Million", to my fucking address?
- 老中 这里面是什么  - 丹 不是你想的那样
- China, what's in this box?  - Dan, it's not what you think it is.
别瞎猜
Don't jump to conclusions.
把垃圾挪走 再把屁股挪开
Shift that bloody rubbish and shift your arse.
我倒要看看这里有什么
I wanna see what's in this box.
我天 哇哦
Oh my God. Wow.
- 你觉得怎么样  - 运动鞋？
- What d'you think of these?  - Bloody trainers?
- 运动鞋  - 运动鞋
- Trainers.  - Trainers.
- 这可都是尖货 丹  - 顶尖的
- These are only the best, Dan.  - Very best.
是不是啊 派普
Aren't they, Piper?
是不是
Aren't they?
别打了 我骨头软
Stop it, man, I've got brittle bones.
丹 给你做个小测试
Anyways, I've got a test for you, Dan.
- 打开吧  - 打开
- Go on, open it.  - Open that.
有区别吗
What's the difference?
这两只鞋有什么区别
Yeah. What's the difference between them two?
看着一样啊
They look the same.
- 就等你这句话  - 没错
- Bang on, brother.  - Exactly.
区别是 这双在名品街要一百五十镑…
The difference is, they'd have cost me 150 quid on the high street...
而我只卖八十镑
And I'm gonna sell those for 80 quid.
卖山寨货 还他妈寄到我家
Cheap counterfeits to my fucking address?
中国黑手党和海关会找上门来的
I could have the Chinese Mafia or the bloody Customs at me door.
你俩真是不要脸到家了
The brass neck of the bloody pair of you.
丹 这些不是山寨货
Dan, these are not counterfeits.
这两双是同一家工厂生产的
They're from the same factory as these.
质量和耐跑度分毫不差
Exactly the same quality. Continuation of the same run.
- 你不信我们吗  - 真他娘的商业奇才
- D'you not believe us?  - It's fucking genius.
你是从哪弄到货的
How d'you manage this?
我一哥们儿 在广州鞋厂工作
Well I know a guy from Guangzhou, don't I, who works in the factory.
人家在工厂工作呢
Yeah, works in the factory.
狂热球迷
He's football mad.
球队球员如数家珍
He knows everything about the teams, the players, everything.
我们用邮件做生意 我用Paypal给他打钱
So we do the deals by e-mails. I send him the money by PayPal,
他再把货寄给我
then he sends me the package by post.
是寄给我吧
Me, you mean.
丹 我原先是想提前打个招呼的 货分批寄给不同的人
Honestly, Dan, I did mean to say, like I get them sent to different mates.
小批量不显眼
You know, small packages like not to attract too much attention.
一般都能顺利过关
They usually get through.
等你俩进了监狱
I'll be able to tell all me mates I knew both of you
我是不会想你们的
before you were arrested.
丹 我的未来
See these trainers, Dan,
就靠这些鞋了
these are the future.
对苦逼的工作说不
No more crap jobs.
对仓库的烂事说不
No more shit from that warehouse.
你知道那帮混蛋今早干了什么
D'you know what the bastards did this morning?
天不亮 五点半 喊我们过去
Got us in at 5:30.
就卸了一卡车货 知道用了多久吗
Unloaded one truck. Guess how long that took?
四十五分钟 知道我报酬多少
Forty-five minutes. And you know how much I got paid?
三镑七毛九分钱啊
Three pound and seventy-nine pence.
他娘的浪费我时间 工资比中国还低
Waste of my fucking time. It's worse than China.
我一定要出人头地 我是认真的
I'm gonna make it big one day, Dan. I'm serious.
您好 需要帮忙吗 您看上去有点迷惑
Hi there, can I help you? You look a bit lost.
我想申请失业津贴…
Aye. I have to apply for Jobseeker's Allowance...
- 这样  - 想用那东西
- Right, yeah. Mmm-hmm.  - And I wanna use one of them
上个因特网
to get on to that Internet web thing.
没问题 今天可以办好
Right, you could do that today.
现在暂时没有空闲的电脑
We're a bit busy at the moment.
您一会儿再来好吗
If you can come back a bit later, would that be okay?
- 点“联络求职中心”  - 嗯
- And then contact Job Centre Plus.  - Mmm-hmm.
就会出现“申请失业津贴”
And, here we are. "Claim Jobseeker's".
- 双击这里  - 好
- Okay? So double-click on that one.  - Okay. All right.
向下滚动鼠标 点击“继续”
And then we need to scroll right the way down here to continue.
这里就是你要的表格
And that's your, that's your form there for you.
你需要拖动鼠标到屏幕上方
So you need to run the mouse up the screen,
点击这里 再输入邮政编码
click into there and pop your postcode in.
- 把鼠标拖到上面 对吗  - 对
- Run the mouse up the screen, yeah? Okay.  - Yeah.
- 不是这样  - 不对吗
- No. No, not quite like that.  - No?
- 要先把光标…  - “光标”？[“骂人”谐音]
- What you need to do is get your cursor...  - "Your cursor"?
名字起得倒不错
It's a fucking apt name for it.
拖动鼠标的时候
So when you're moving your mouse,
- 看到我的动作了吗  - 嗯 看到了
- you see what I'm doing with my hand?  - Aye, right.
- 看我的手  - 好 就像这样
- Look at my hand.  - Aye. Oh, right, it moves like that.
- 点击“继续”  - 好
- And then continue.  - Right, okay.
- 然后从这里开始就行  - 好
- And then you start from there. Okay?  - Okay.
- 那后面的您自己来吧  - 好
- I'll leave you with it. Okay?  - Right.
好吧
Right.
不好意思 能来帮帮我吗
Excuse me, pet. You couldn't help us with this, could you?
好 怎么了
Yeah. What is it?
我在填表 打不上字
I'm just filling this in. I'm just... I cannot get the...
这东西老是四处乱窜
This keeps darting all over the place.
我该怎么办 我是不是要…
What do I do? Do I get on to that and...
怎么把这个拉下来啊
Do you just... I mean, how do you get this down?
移动鼠标 点击这个竖栏
Right, so you're controlling this, and you click on this bar.
- 好  - 向下拖动
- Right.  - And then you pull it down.
- 哦这样  - 然后就…
- Oh, right.  - And then you get...
- 按住对吗 好  - 接下来的就在这了
- What, do I hold that on there, do I? Okay.  - The rest of it. Yeah.
- 好 然后…  - 左键
- All right, then I can just...  - On the left side.
拖住后向下拉对吗
What, what, so I hold this and just pull that down?
- 对 点击左键  - 点击…
- Yeah, and click the left.  - And click...
- 点击左键  - 好
- Click to the left.  - Yeah. Right.
放这就行了 哦 太感谢了
And I just put that in there? Oh, that's right, thanks very much.
- 没事  - 哇
- It's fine.  - Aye.
姑娘真是厉害
You're a star. Right.
好了 做对没有 看看…
Right, have I done it right? There we are...
妈的 这又是什么
Oh, bloody hell. What's this now?
“错误”？
"Error"?
我这又是…
Well, what have I...
哥们 你知道我这是哪里做错了吗
Here, mate, you divvent know what I've done here, do you?
- 这显示错误  - 是啊 好大的错误提示
- This error thing.  - Yeah, that's a big thing.
你帮我看看 我填表的时候突然就…
Do you? I don't know, I was just filling in the thing and it just went...
- 行了  - 噢 好了
- There we go.  - Oh, oh, yeah, there we go.
哦 又回来了 太好了
We're back on, right.
- 回来了对吧  - 你能多呆一会吗
- You're sorted, yeah?  - Hey, can you just hang on
我怕又出错
just for two seconds so I divvent go back here again. I'll...
等我再多填几题
Just, just, just, I'll just like do a couple more questions.
放心 我在
Yeah, I'll just stand over here, don't worry.
“你是否 是”
Er... "Are you a Br..."
- 对  - 我选择“是”
- Yeah.  - "Yes". Right. I do that.
- 好  - 对
- Right. What?  - Yeah.
- 这个…  - 然后继续就行了
- What's...  - Then you should continue.
应该没问题
Should be all right.
行
Right, okay.
然后…
What's...
这个不对…
It's, it's, it's not bloody, it's not...
- 怎么一动不动  - 稍微等一下
- Well nowt's happening now.  - Yeah, just give it a second.
等一下的
Just give it a second.
可这 瞧 压根儿就不动了
But it's just not mov... I mean, look, it's not even, it's not even moving.
- 我来试试吧  - 鼠标给你
- Let me try, right.  - What? Here, get that.
太抓狂了 不知又做错了什么
This is driving me mental, this. I mean, what have I done now?
- 死机了  - 死机
- It's frozen. Yeah.  - It's frozen?
能让它复活吗
Well... Well, can you defrost it?
这我不行
No, mate, I can't.
你的时间到了
Think your time's up.
- 什么  - 你的时间到了
- What?  - Your time's up.
- 我的时间到了？ - 是 很抱歉 哥们
- Me time's up?  - Yeah, I'm sorry, mate.
很抱歉
Oh, sorry, mate, yeah.
- 我先走了  - 天哪
- I'll just leave you to it.  - Oh jeez.
- 有没有配偶  - 没有 我老婆去世了
- Do you have a partner?  - Er, no. She, er, she's passed away.
- 太遗憾了  - 谢谢
- Oh, I'm really sorry to hear that.  - Thank you.
是否有二十岁以下 尚未独立的子女同住
D'you have any dependent children aged under 20 living with you?
没有
No, I don't.
把这个表填好是很重要的 填好后才能开始评估程序
It's really important we get this filled in because we need to get the process started.
好
Yeah.
不好意思 安 能跟你谈谈吗
Excuse me, Ann. Can I have a word, please?
等我三十秒 我们马上就…
Could you just give me 30 seconds, please? We're just getting...
现在就去我的办公室谈
Well, actually, can I have a word now, in my office?
谢谢
Thank you.
- 好吧  - 天呐 我给你惹麻烦了
- Right.  - Jesus, I've got you into trouble now.
- 真是对不起  - 我才应该说对不起
- I'm really sorry.  - It's me that should be sorry.
那继续填吧 你做得很好
You just carry on, you're doing good.
安 我跟你说过这个问题
You know, Ann, we've spoke about this before.
这种做法是不可接受的
That isn't acceptable.
- 我认为他这个情况应该通融…  - 到办公室里来
- I think in this case it's quite reasonable...  - Come on in the office.
你开了一个不好的先例
The thing is you're setting a precedent.
坚决不行
It's not acceptable.
烦死了…
Oh, bugger. Bugger, it's...
天哪…
Jesus...
简直不敢相信
I don't believe this.
不，我只想分享我喜欢的足球
No, I only want my share of the football.
东北部知道纽卡斯尔联队就够了
Right then, that's the only team you need to know in the northeast, is Newcastle.
你还听说过其它球队吗
What other teams do you know?
- 呃 米… 米德尔斯堡队  - 米德尔斯堡队
- Er, Middle... Middle-borough.  - Middlesbrough, aye.
- 米德尔斯堡队 对  - 米德尔斯堡队
- Middlesbrough. Yeah.  - Middlesbrough.
这破队不用你费神去知道
You know, you divvent need to think about them either. Aye?
给
There you go.
就剩一块派了 我切成了四块
Er, we only have one Wagon Wheel left, so I cut it into four.
你吃两块 因为你是主人
But you can have two pieces considering you're the host.
好嘞 我把你的茶放在这
Oh, there you go. I'll put your tea down there.
- 噢等等  - 巴克莱英超联赛
- Oh, hang on.  - Barclay's Premier League.
最重要的问题来了 史丹李
Here's the big question, Stan Li.
你叫他“斯坦利”？
Did you say "Stan Li"?
对 广州的史丹李
Yeah. Stan Li from Guangzhou.
你俩合着伙蒙我呢
Are you two winding me up?
那不是我们的风格
No, that's not our style.
能听见吗 史丹李
Can you hear me, Stan Li?
英超最喜欢的球员是？
Favourite player in the Premier?
查理·亚当 斯托克城队的
Charlie Adams, Stoke City.
滚蛋 你丫开什么玩笑
Get the fuck out of here.
不是开玩笑吧
Are, are you taking the piss?
英超真是人傻钱多 哥们儿
EPL is crazy money, man.
查理·亚当斯 才四百万英镑
Charlie Adam. Four million.
不独
No ego.
团队型球员
Team player.
狠角色
Tough guy.
对阵切尔西 在本方半场的那脚超远吊射
You see his goal against Chelsea from his own half?
砰
Boom!
球高高飞起 越过门将库尔图瓦头顶 进球啦
The ball flies up, over Courtois' head. Cross the line, line. Goal!
他才不在中国 他不就是路边外卖店小哥吗
He's not in China. He's in the bloody takeaway down the road.
你俩被骗啦
You two, you're taking the piss.
史丹李 我会把最终报价发给你 我的最高价
Okay, Stan Li, I'll e-mail you my best price. Top price.
先看看卖得如何
I'm gonna see how I get on selling these ones I've got, okay?
保持联系
So I'll let you know.
最高价哦 别扯淡哦
Best price, no bullshit.
记住 查理 查理 钞票大帝
Remember, Charlie Charlie, all good money.
不是最高价 不给运动鞋
Okay, no best price, no more trainer.
不跟你做生意
No more business.
不跟你瞎蛋逼 不跟你唱…
No more talkie-talkie. No more...
♫ 轻轻摇 我的小马车 ♫
♪ Swing low, sweet chariot ♪
♫ 载我回故乡 ♫
♪ Coming for to carry me home ♪
丹 确认你的国家保险号
Right, Dan. Check your National Insurance Number.
嗯 没错
Yep, that's okay.
按下那个键 比尔盖茨先生
Press that button right there, Bill Gates.
- 这个键吗  - 那个 发送键
- What, this one here?  - That one there, "Send."
这表格折磨了我好几天
Huh. It's taken me bloody days to get this sorted out.
干得漂亮 小伙子
Well done, son.
失业津贴申请表 完成
Jobseeker's Application done.
丹 你有心脏病怎么还申请这个
Dan, don't know why you're applying for that after your heart attack.
现在 我就来打印你的就业支持津贴申诉表
Right, now I'm printing your appeal form for Employment and Support Allowance.
但要等强制再评估后才能申诉
But you can't appeal till they carry out a mandatory reconsideration.
这就在打印了吗
Is that printing out now?
所以 他们其实当场就能给我
You mean, they could have given it to me just like that?
丹 他们会耍得你团团转 给你提个醒
Dan, they'll fuck you around, I'm warning you.
你会生不如死
Make it as miserable as possible.
这是他们的本意 绝无例外
No accident. That's the plan.
我知道很多人直接放弃了
I know dozens who have just given up.
如果他们觉得我会放弃 那就大错特错了
Well they've picked the wrong one if they think I'm gonna give up.
逮住骨头的狗是不会撒口的
I'm like a dog with a bone, me, son.
先生 我这里记录显示
I have a note on the screen, sir,
您正在等待决策者的电话
that you're awaiting a call from the decision maker.
等了五十五分钟 又绕回来了
Jesus, 55 minutes to hear all this again.
我难道是在时间隧道吗
Am I in a time warp?
您只有在接到
You can't proceed to the appeal
决策者的电话后
or the mandatory reconsideration
才能申诉或进行强制性再评估
till you have the call from the decision maker.
你能让他们现在就打吗 因为我没有收入
Well, can you ask him to phone us now, because I've got no income.
没有养老金 还要交卧室税
I've got no pension and I've still got the bedroom tax.
我会将此情况录入电脑 先生
I'll make a note on my screen, sir.
能传个纸条给他吗
Well can you not give him the note now?
直接放他手里
You know, put it in his hand?
这里是热线中心 先生
This is a call centre, sir.
迪伦 想不想玩玩螺丝刀啊
Hey, Dylan. D'you want a shot at the screwdriver?
哪一个杀人更多 椰子还是鲨鱼
What kills more people, coconuts or sharks?
那孩子拍球都入迷了
He likes bouncing that ball, doesn't he?
什么
Pardon?
那个球 他天天拍个不停
That ball. He likes bouncing it, doesn't he?
我们挤在临时救济房的时候 他就这样了
Well, it started in the hostel where we had only one small room.
你觉得是为什么呢
Why d'you think he does that?
可能是想他的朋友了吧
I think he's missing his friends.
但他生气的时候也会拍球
But he also does it when he's angry.
别人从不听他说话 他为什么要听别人呢
People never listen to him, so why should he listen to them?
好了 贴这个可不需要胶水
There you go. And we don't need any glue, nothing like that.
你帮我把这个贴到窗户上
Now you give me a hand and we'll stick this up.
你抓那头 我抓这头
Right, you go that end and I'll go this end.
贴在这里
And we'll stick this up here.
还有这里
Yeah? Just pass it up here.
你把底下铺平 对了
Aye, right. You do the bottom edge. That's it.
太阳会把泡泡里的空气烤热
The sun heats up all the air in these bubbles...
你们的房间就暖和了
And it'll keep your room nice and warm.
帮我从工具包里拿点东西
Can you go into my tool bag there,
就是那个布包
there's a piece of cloth.
能打开吗
Can you open it?
嗯？
Eh?
- 怎么样啊  - 好漂亮啊
- What do you think of that?  - It's gorgeous.
这是给你们新家的小礼物
Well it's a little present for your new room.
- 现在…  - 谢谢
- Now...  - Thank you.
- 放在哪好呢  - 挂在上面吧
- Where shall we put it?  - Up there, maybe.
好 等一下啊
Okay, hang on.
我找个钩子挂上
I'll get a hook and hang it there.
你觉得怎样
Yeah, what do you think?
真好
It's great.
就像住在海底世界一样
It'll look like you're under the sea.
阳光照在它们身上
And the sun will shine on them.
一切都会好好的
I think there will be fine, yeah?
我来点蜡烛
I'll light these candles.
- 哇哦  - 对呀
- Whoa.  - Yeah.
- 等一下  - 好大的火
- Now hang on.  - That one's big.
没错 有四根蜡烛对吗
It is. Now there's four candles. Right?
别烫到手
Mind you don't burn yourself.
不会烫到手的 别担心
I won't burn meself, don't worry about that.
但谢谢你的关心 黛西
But thank you for thinking about us, Daisy.
那根点好了
Put that in there like that.
这根放在这 四根蜡烛都点好了
And I put this one in here. Now there's four candles in there, right.
能烧四个小时呢
And they last for four hours.
我把这个小花盆盖上
I'll put this small pot over. Right?
堵住上面的洞
Block the hole off up there.
再用一个大花盆套住
And then I put this big pot over the top.
再等一段时间 屋子里就暖和了
Now it takes a little while but it'll take the chill off the room.
把手放在上面就有热气了 黛西你试试
And if you just put your hand over there now, you'll feel it, Daisy.
把手放在这 是不是很暖和
If you just put your hand over there, you'll feel it starting to warm up.
- 感觉到了吗  - 有一点
- Huh, can you feel it? Yeah?  - A little bit.
- 你呢  - 有一点
- What about you?  - Yeah, a little bit.
你以前当过兵吗 丹
Were you a soldier, Dan?
当兵？
Was I a soldier?
比那危险多了呢 我是木匠
Oh, more dangerous than that. I was a carpenter.
饭好了
Right, grub's ready.
- 耶  - 坐那边去 迪伦
- Yay!  - Go round that way then, Dylan.
乖 这是你的
Good boy. There's yours, poppet.
把狗狗放在那边
Right, put Sweet on there.
都坐好
Sit down nicely then.
- 丹 这是你的  - 谢谢 我不吃
- And, Dan, this one's yours.  - Oh, no, not for me, thanks, no.
这是你的
That's yours. All right?
吃吧
Here you are. All right?
- 你不吃吗  - 我已经吃过了
- Well, where's yours?  - I had mine earlier.
再吃点水果就行了
I'm just gonna have a bit of fruit.
你昨天和前天也是这么说的
You said that yesterday, and the day before.
好了 快吃吧
All right, eat up then.
看上去很美味 但我饭点没这么早
Looks delicious but, you know, it's a wee... It's a wee bit early for me.
吃吧 丹 这是我的一点心意
Please, Dan. It's the least I can do.
- 谢谢 凯蒂  - 吃吧
- Thank you, Katie.  - All right.
刚才是什么声音 妈妈
What was that sound, Mum?
打扫浴室的时候 有块瓷砖
Oh, babe, one of the tiles just fell off the wall in the bathroom
掉下来了
where I was cleaning it.
都半夜了
It's the middle of the night.
- 我知道  - 你该去睡觉了
- I know.  - You should really get to bed.
好 我马上就去睡
Okay. I'm gonna go to bed.
我马上就去睡
I'm gonna go to bed.
我想赶快把浴室打扫干净
I just wanted to get all the cleaning done in there
明天你们就能泡澡了
so you can have a nice bath tomorrow.
你喜欢泡澡 对吗
You like a bath, don't ya?
嗯
Yeah?
上楼睡觉 把被子掖好
So you're gonna go up and get into bed and wrap up nicely.
好吗 乖孩子 亲亲妈妈
Okay, good girl. Give me a kiss.
快去睡觉
Go and get into bed.
- 好吗  宝贝  - 你保证会去睡觉
- All right? Good girl.  - Promise me you'll get to bed.
我保证马上就去
I promise you I'm gonna go to bed.
- 晚安  - 晚安 宝贝
- Good night.  - 'Night, baby.
丹尼尔·布莱克？
Daniel Blake?
请跟我来 布莱克先生
If you'd like to follow me, Mr Blake.
请坐
If you'd like to just take a seat.
这是申诉人承诺表格
This is the Claimant Commitment form.
你要保证每周用三十五小时的时间求职
You must commit yourself to spending 35 hours a week looking for work.
可以通过报纸求职栏 求职中介
Now that can be newspapers, agencies,
或是政府的求职网站
and online via the Universal Job Match.
只需填好相关细节即可
You just fill in the details.
但您需要证明您确实在找工作
But you must prove that you've done this as well, mind.
医生说我暂时还不能工作
Well I've been told by my doctor that I'm not supposed to go back to work yet.
那您就应该申请就业支持津贴
Then you should apply for Employment and Support Allowance.
我申请了 但被一个冒牌医生驳回了
I have, but I've been knocked back by some quack
所以现在还要申诉
and now I'm trying to appeal.
那是您的选择 布莱克先生
Okay. Well that's your choice, Mr Blake.
不 这不是我的选择
No, it's not my choice.
我没有任何收入来源
I've got no other form of income.
您到底要不要签字
Do you want to sign this or not?
只需要签上您的名字 我会把日期填好
You just need to put your signature here. I shall date it later on.
谢谢
Thank you.
我能看一下您的简历吗
Now can I have a look at your CV?
什么简历
"CV"?
您还是不懂 布莱克先生
You still don't get this, do you, Mr Blake?
这是您和政府间的协议
This is an agreement between you and the State.
不 是你不懂
No, you still don't get it.
- 不 你必须…  - 我很想回去工作
- No, you must...  - I'm desperate to go back to work.
- 如果您很想回去工作…  - 但医生告诉我…
- If you're desperate to get back to work...  - Unless the doctor tells us...
就需要一份最新的简历
You need to have an up-to-date CV,
来帮助您找工作
in order to help you look for work.
请您先等一下
Now, just hold it right there.
我希望您能去参加简历撰写训练班
There's a CV workshop that I would like you to attend
时间是这周六早上九点
and it's this Saturday at 9:00.
不用了 我自己搞定吧
No, thanks, I'll sort that out on me own.
不 布莱克先生 这是正式指令
No, Mr Blake. This is a formal direction.
想拿到失业津贴就必须参加
You will attend if you want to proceed with your Jobseeker's Allowance claim.
我要是不去呢
What happens if I don't?
那您就可能会受处罚
Then you will be referred for a sanction.
十秒钟
Ten seconds.
短短的十秒钟
Ten short seconds.
这是雇主浏览简历所用的平均时间
That's how much a typical employer spends flipping through a CV.
千真万确
Fact.
每份低技术含量工作有六十个人竞争
Sixty applications for every low-skilled job.
千真万确
Fact.
高技术含量工作竞争比例二十比一
For a skilled job, it's twenty to one.
千真万确
Fact.
科斯塔咖啡招聘八个岗位
Costa Coffee advertised eight jobs.
知道有多少人应聘吗
D'you know how many applications they got from that?
超过一千三百个
Over 1,300.
千真万确
Fact.
这代表什么呢
So, what does that mean?
代表咱都应该可劲喝咖啡
We should all be drinking a lot more bloody coffee.
您再说一遍 让大家都听听
Yeah, d'you wanna share that with us?
我说 咱都应该可劲喝咖啡
I said, we should all be drinking a lot more bloody coffee then.
求职形势严峻
This is serious business
每人只有一次机会
and people have only got one shot at this, all right?
凡是会数数的人都知道 没有足够的工作岗位 千真万确
Well if you can count, it's obvious. There's not enough jobs. Fact.
那你就永远落后于人吧
Yeah, well, you'll be at the back of the queue, won't you?
对我们这些要面对现实的人来说
For those of us in the real world,
这代表
what that means is...
“你必须在竞争中”
"You must stand
“脱颖而出”
"out from the crowd."
要吸睛 要上位
Get noticed. Get smart.
只展示技能
It's not enough these days just to, er,
是远远不够的
just to show you have the skills.
你要证明
You have to prove
你的敏锐和专注
how keen you are. How dedicated.
好
Okay...
我希望大家能将简历重新排版
What I'd like you to do now is to, er, format your CVs.
切记 字体要清晰
And, remember, all of these have to be typed up in a clear font
并打印成纸质
in hard copy.
还需要用于网上申请的电子版
And we're also gonna need a digital version for online.
有些公司
And some companies,
还要求用智能手机发送视频简历
they're demanding CV videos, sent in by smartphone.
时代发展多快啊
How about that?
好的 开始吧
Okay? Let's make a start.
哥们 你这招人吗
Are you taking any blokes on, mate?
我是个木匠 正在找活儿干呢
I'm a joiner, you know I'm just looking for some work, you know.
目前不招人
Not at the minute. Er, all manned up.
我留个简历 有需要再联系吧
Okay, can, can I give you my CV? And then if you can get in touch...
- 不好意思 哥们  - 什么事
- Excuse me, mate.  - Yeah.
你知道这附近哪家在招人吗
D'you know if anybody's taking anybody on round here?
我们这不招人
Er, no, we're not taking anyone on.
你不如这样
Er, I'll tell you what you could do.
向左走三户
If you try about three units up on the left there,
那家可能有空缺
they'll probably... They, they might be havin' one.
- 好 谢了  - 来吧 干杯 伙计
- Okay, thanks.  - Okay? Cheers, mate.
- 你最好跟他说  - 他是老板吗
- Your best bet is to see him.  - Is he the boss? Him?
是 他是监工 这的老板
He's, he's the supervisor. That's the boss there.
不好意思 哥们 这招不招人啊
Excuse me, mate. D'you know if they're taking anybody on here?
有没有工作啊
Have you got any jobs ganning?
哦 没有吗
No, you haven't?
我在找工作
Hey, mate, I'm looking for some work.
- 你知道这附近哪里招人吗  - 这可没什么活
- Is there anything ganning on around here?  - There's nowt here, mate. There's...
再远点可能有
There might be something, erm, a bit further up,
- 试试别的地方吧  - 是吗
- if you try one of the other estates, but...  - Yeah?
这附近是没有了
...nothing doing on here.
有事吗
Help you, mate?
我在找工作
Aye, I was just looking for some work, mate.
不知你这招不招人
I was wondering if you had anything ganning on?
还真有
I might have.
- 是吗  - 干过这活吗
- Aye?  - Done this graft before?
- 有经验吗  - 我有四十年经验
- You got any experience?  - Oh, I've got 40 years of experience, mate.
手可巧着呢 能把简历给你吗
I can turn me hand to owt. Can I give you me CV?
当然 我看看
Way-ay, course, I'll have a look at it.
给你
There you go.
谢了
Cheers.
- 丹尼尔  - 对 就是我
- Daniel?  - Aye, that's me.
我叫哈利
I'm Harry, by the way.
你经验够丰富的 老实说
Well, you've got plenty of experience, like, I've gotta be honest,
我受够年轻人了
I'm absolutely sick of young'uns.
要么旷工 要么懒得要死
Half the time they divvent turn up. When they do, they cannot be arsed.
迪伦 快点 跟上
Dylan, Dylan, come off the road, come on.
快
Come on.
迪伦 跟上 快
Dylan, come on. Catch up. Come on.
- 这是食品救济站的队吗  - 是
- Is this the, er, queue for the food bank?  - It is, aye.
大概要等多久啊
D'you know how long we'll be waiting?
很长时间吧 我都排了好久了
Oh, a canny long time, I reckon. We've been here ages already.
好吧 谢谢
Okay, thanks. Cheers.
- 你们好啊  - 你好
- Hello.  - Hello.
很高兴见到你
How nice to see you.
今天把小狗带来啦
Have you brought your little dog today?
非常感谢 谢谢
Thank you very much, thank you.
是领你和孩子们的食物吗 凯蒂 谢谢
Is it just food for yourself and the two children, Katie? Thank you.
给孩子们拿点饼干和果汁吧
Would your children have a drink of juice and a biscuit?
你去找阿格尼丝吧
Would you like to go and see Agnes?
阿格尼丝 请拿点果汁和饼干
Agnes? Could you do a juice and a biscuit, please?
- 杰琪  - 在
- Jackie?  - Yeah.
你来帮凯蒂领东西好吗
Would you be able to help Katie with her shopping today, please?
- 来  - 谢谢
- There you are.  - Thank you.
- 你好 凯蒂  - 谢谢
- Hiya, Katie.  - Thank you.
一个大人 两个孩子 跟我来吧
So, we've got one adult and two children, yeah? Come with me.
- 先领蔬菜 好吗  - 好
- We'll start with the vegetables, yeah?  - Okay.
好的
Right.
袋子咱们一起拎着
I'll give you one side and we'll share it, yeah?
- 两个洋葱  - 您需要什么吗
- Couple of onions.  - Is there anything we can do for you, hun?
- 不用 谢谢  - 确定吗
- No, I'm fine, thanks.  - Are you sure?
- 好吧  - 日用品
- Aye, all right then.  - Toiletries, yeah?
好
Okay...
你刚搬来吧 听口音不是本地人
Have you just moved up here? Your accent's not from here.
- 不是北方姑娘吧  - 是啊 搬来有一阵了
- You're not a Geordie girl.  - Yeah. Yeah, been up a little while.
从伦敦来的
Just come up from London.
口音真好听
Right. Nice accent.
听得懂北方口音吗
Can you understand the Geordies?
差不多吧
Almost.
好 这边
Right, over here.
还得再拿个袋子 还有吗
I think we need another bag. Have we got one?
你们是坐公交来的吗
Did you bus here?
- 没有 有时候吧  - 有时候啊
- No? Well, sometimes.  - Well, sometimes.
她有时候喜欢喝茶
She likes tea sometimes.
- 我就自己帮你拿了啊  - 好
- Well, I'll just keep going in with stuff.  - Yeah.
你告诉我哪些是你不要的
And then you tell me what you don't need, yeah?
有卫生巾吗
Have you got any sanitary towels?
- 我们没有卫生巾  - 没有？没关系
- We don't have sanitary towels, no.  - No? All right, not to worry. It's all right.
- 没什么人捐卫生巾  - 也是
- Don't really donate things much like that.  - Yeah.
太可惜了 应该多捐点
It's a shame, they should.
把袋子打开 装点米
Right, right, if you open your bag. Rice?
- 拿几卷卫生纸吧  - 嗯
- And a couple of toilet rolls?  - Mmm-hmm.
好了
Yeah?
去食品柜吧 都掉出来了
We'll go to the food. It's falling out me bag.
- 你把这个…  - 我拿这个
- You can put...  - I've got this one. Right.
拿点罐头吧 放在这
Erm, tins in yours. Put them in there.
还有什么想要的
Can you see anything else you want?
- 拿着  - 谢谢
- There you go.  - Okay, thank you.
- 那边有意大利面酱  - 嗯
- Erm, there's pasta sauce over here.  - Mmm-hmm.
我给你拿点意大利面酱
I'll get you some pasta sauce?
意大利面酱…
The pasta sauce...
这里还有意大利面
And there's, er, pasta here as well. I'll get you a pasta.
亲爱的 你没事吧 你在干什么呢
Hey, pet, are you all right? What are you doing? What are you doing?
快坐会吧 没事
Come and sit down. It's all right. It's all right, it's all right.
坐下吧 快坐下 没事了
Come and sit down. Come and sit down, it's all right.
噢…
Oh...
好啦 没关系
Okay, it's all right. It's all right, it's all right.
没事了 想喝点什么吗
It's all right. D'you want a drink?
- 想喝点什么吗  - 真的对不起…
- D'you want a drink?  - I'm really sorry...
- 怎么了  - 没事 别担心
- What's the matter?  - It's okay, don't worry.
- 我去给你拿点喝的  - 妈妈 怎么了
- I'll get you a drink.  - Mum, what's going on?
没事 没事
It's okay. It's okay
我就是太饿了
I'm just really hungry.
- 别这样看着我  - 没事 没关系的
- Okay, don't look at me.  - No, no, no, it's okay, it's okay.
没什么大不了的
There's no harm done.
我撑不下去了 丹 我要崩溃了
I can't cope, Dan. I feel like I'm going under.
你会撑过去的 你会的亲爱的
Look, you'll get through this, darling.
- 谢谢  - 你会撑过去的
- Thank you.  - You'll get through this.
凯蒂 听我说 这不是你的错
Katie, listen to me. This isn't your fault.
你很了不起
You've done amazing.
被扔到这个地方 还带着两个孩子
Dumped up here, on your own with two kids.
这没什么可羞愧的
You've done nothing to be ashamed of.
真的没事
Come on, you're okay.
擦擦眼泪
Come on, wipe yourself.
没事的
Come on... You're okay.
- 要是我妈知道我沦落成这样…  - 没事的
- If my mum could see me...  - It's okay.
大家都在帮你
Look, these people are here to help you.
没什么可羞愧的
You know, you've done nothing to be ashamed of.
- 真对不起  - 不 你很好
- I'm so sorry.  - No, no, you're all right.
- 还需要什么吗  - 我刚才头特别晕
- Can I get you anything else?  - I just felt really faint.
要纸巾吗 或者湿巾
D'you need some paper tissues or baby wipes?
- 我去给你拿点湿巾  - 谢谢
- I'll get you some baby wipes.  - Thank you.
我刚才头好晕
I felt really faint.
凯蒂 想吃点什么吗 给你盛点汤吧
Katie, can I get you something to eat? Would you like some soup or something?
能给她拿点水吗
Yeah, yeah, yeah... If you could get her some water.
什么都行 你要不要吃点东西
Sure, yeah, anything. Yeah. You not want some food?
- 那麻烦…  - 吃点甜的
- Yeah, please, get...  - Even something sugary.
我去给你拿个甜甜圈
I'll get you a doughnut or something.
怎样
Yeah, yeah?
没有中间商 直接厂家提货
There's no middlemen. Straight from the factory.
跟专卖店质量一样
Same quality as the shop.
- 完全一样  - 便宜点吧
- Same quality, exactly.  - Well, you're gonna have to do us a deal.
八十镑太贵了
I couldn't pay 80 quid for this, though.
专卖店一百五十镑一双
If you go to the shop, they're 150 pounds.
- 一百五？ - 我这才八十
- A hundred and fifty quid?  - I'm selling these for 80 pounds.
- 什么叫才八十  - 上面还有标签呢
- Only 80 quid.  - See, they've still got the stickers on.
为什么只卖八十
Why are they 80?
只卖八十是因为没有中间商赚差价
The reason they're 80 is because there's no middlemen, nothing.
- 谁都没有  - 看看你俩 商业新贵啊
- No middlemen, whatsoever.  - You and Piper, the top new businessmen.
这是我司机 丹
That's my driver, Dan.
司机你个头
I'll give you a bloody driver.
这不是二手的吧
So no-one's worn them before?
绝对不是 您瞅瞅这质量
No-one's wore them. Nothing, look. Check the quality yourself.
我可以穿去健身房
I'd probably wear them for the gym.
八十镑不行 实在太贵了
I couldn't say 80 quid, mate. This is too expensive for 80 quid.
- 专卖店卖一百五呢  - 一百五
- They're 150 pound in the shop.  - A hundred and fifty pound, yeah.
- 丹 哥们 你还好吗  - 你好 乔
- Oh, Dan. You all right, mate?  - Hello, Joe.
- 挺好的  - 最近怎么样
- Aye, I'm all right, mate, aye.  - How are you doing?
我们今晚去酒吧聚聚
Erm, listen, we're ganning, erm... We're away down the pub the night.
不少人呢 还有乐队
There's a load of us ganning. There's a band on, you know.
我会去喝两杯 一起吧
We're gonna sink a few pints. D'you fancy, fancy coming down?
馋死我了 但医生说不能沾酒
Aye, I'd murder a pint, mate, but I daresn't. I've been telt to lay off the sauce, you know.
- 是吗  - 我会回锯木厂
- Oh, really?  - But, listen, tell the lads I'll come down
看大家的 好吗
and pop into the sawmill, eh?
好
Oh, aye, aye, aye.
我们今晚都在 能来就来吧
You know, if you fancy it anyway, we're all going down.
那回头见吧
So we might see you later, mate.
- 见到你真好 哥们  - 回见了
- Nice to see you, man.  - See you then. Ta-ta, see you.
丹尼尔·布莱克的语音留言
Message for Daniel Blake.
我是就业和养老金部的决策者
Mr Blake, this is a call from the DWP decision maker.
你会很快收到
You should soon receive a letter
判定您符合工作条件
which states that you have been deemed fit for work
并无法申请职业支持津贴的信件
and not entitled to Employment and Support Allowance.
如需更多信息
If you need any further information,
请上网查询 谢谢
it's available online. Thank you.
终于他妈打来了
Fuck's sake.
- 喂  - 你好 请问是丹尼尔吗
- Hello?  - Hi, is that Daniel?
是我 你好
Yes, it is. Hi.
你好 我是哈利·爱德华兹
Hi, Daniel, it's Harry Edwards here.
前几天我们在花园中心见过面…
We spoke the other day at the garden centre...
- 哦对  - …当时你给了简历给我的
- Oh, yeah, yeah.  - ...when you came down and handed your CV.
- 你最近还好吧  - 挺好 谢谢
- How are you doing, mate? Are you all right?  - Yeah, yeah, I'm fine, thanks, yeah.
我刚刚筛选了这几周
Er, listen. I tell you what, mate, I've been going through all the CVs
收到的简历
I've had handed over the last couple of weeks.
我很喜欢你
And I really like the look of yours.
你的经验正是我需要的
Erm, you've got the experience I'm looking for.
你明天是否能来面试
I was wondering if you could possibly, er, pop by tomorrow and that for an interview?
很抱歉 爱德华兹先生
Oh... I'm really sorry, er, Mr Edwards,
医生说我的身体状况不适合工作
but, you know, er, my doctor's told us I cannae come back to work yet.
所以你不是真的在找工作？
So you're not actually looking for work, then?
这 说来话长
Well, it's hard to explain, you know.
你不找工作
So, well, what's the point of handing in your CV
给我简历干嘛呢？
if you're not looking for work?
只有这样才能领到福利
Well it's the only way I can get me benefits, you know?
“福利”？原来你是那种吃福利的懒人啊
"Benefits"? So you prefer to be on benefits than do a day's graft?
我还以为你是个实诚人呢
You know, I thought you were a genuine bloke.
我筛选简历用了很长时间
You know, I've spent a lot of time going through them all.
本想给你点活干
I've... I was gonna put some graft your way.
你却浪费我的时间 赶紧滚吧
You've just wasted my time completely. Why don't you just sod right off!
听着 我不是…
Listen, that's not...
- 这是零钱和收据  - 谢谢
- That's your change and your receipt.  - Thank you.
- 谢谢惠顾  - 再见
- Thank you very much. Have a good day.  - Bye.
- 再见  - 谢谢 再见
- Bye.  - Thank you, bye.
不好意思 小姐 您刚才从店里偷了东西
Excuse me, madam. I think you've been shoplifting.
请跟我到经理办公室谈谈
Would you like to come with me to the manager's office and we can sort it out?
我没偷东西
I haven't been shoplifting.
你偷了 我看见了 请跟我走…
Okay, you have, and I've seen you. So if you'd like to come with me...
可我有收据啊
No, I've got a receipt. I've got, I've just,
- 那位女士刚才给我结账的  - 如果你身上的东西
- the lady there's just served me.  - Okay, and if everything on your receipt
都在收据上 就没事
is all you've got on you, then there's no problem.
请您先跟我去经理办公室吧
If you'd just like to come this way to the manager's office.
我不去
No, I'm not going to the manager's office.
收银员明明给我结账了 我有收据
You just stood there and watched her serve me, I've got a receipt.
我也可以立即锁门报警
I can lock the door and call the police.
你要锁门报警
You're talking about locking the door and calling the police.
请跟我来
Would you like to come with me to the manager's office?
你看见我结账了
No, because I've just, you've just watched me...
我们去了再解决
Okay, and we'll sort that out.
包里的东西都在收据上
Okay, and if everything on the receipt's in your bags,
- 那就没事  - 那你也不用嚷嚷啊
- then there's no problem.  - You don't need to shout at me.
请这边走
Okay, if you'd like to come this way.
你明明看见我
She's just, you've just stood there and watched it...
- 我们会解决的  - …结账了啊
- Okay, then we'll sort it out.  - ...and serve me with, didn't you?
她还给了我收据
And she's given me a receipt.
这边
Just this way.
埃文 这事交给我吧
Ivan, I'll take it from here.
你叫什么名字
What's your name, love?
- 凯蒂  - 凯蒂？
- Katie.  - Katie?
- 凯蒂·摩根  - 凯蒂·摩根
- Katie Morgan.  - Katie Morgan.
真的很抱歉
I'm really sorry.
我从没偷过东西 这些都付过钱了
I haven't done anything like this before. I've paid for these.
你打算怎么办
What are you gonna do?
凯蒂
Katie.
这事你知 我知
It's between me and you...
跟超市没关系 好吗
It's got nowt to do with the store. All right?
我就当你付过钱了
They're paid for.
你可以走了
Get yoursel' away.
谢谢
Thank you.
嘿 等等 等一下
Hey, hang on a second. Hey, hang on...
刚才的事我很抱歉 真的
I'm sorry about that, I am.
能跟你私下说句话吗
Can I get a quiet word?
如果你急需用钱 我能帮你
Look, if you're in trouble and you need money, I can help, okay?
你这么漂亮的女孩 我肯定有办法
Look, a nice girl like you, I can definitely help.
这是我的电话号码 我叫埃文
That's my number. My name's Ivan, okay?
有需要随时打给我
Ring me any time, all right?
好吗
Okay?
你过来看看他
Come and have a look at this.
简直是奇迹
That is a miracle.
他安静地坐了整整十五分钟
He's been sat there for about 15 minutes.
丹 这是什么
What's this, Dan?
卡带
It's a cassette.
卡带是什么
What's a cassette?
放音乐的 来 我放给你看
Plays music. Come here, I'll show you.
好
All right.
放进去 得先从盒子里拿出来
You pop that in there. Oh, no, you gotta take it out the case first.
要不没法放
It'll not play like that.
好 现在就能放进去了
Right, you put that in there like that. Yeah?
按这个按钮
And press that button there.
再用点劲儿
Bit more. Harder.
对啦
That's it.
这是莫莉的卡带
It was Molly's.
她从广播上录下来的
She recorded it off the radio.
海上天气播报的音乐
Shipping forecast.
深夜的节目
It's on late at night.
曲名是《远航》 好听吗
Sailing By. D'you like that tune?
- 好听  - 莫莉特别爱听
- Yeah.  - Yeah, Molly loved it.
真是好听
It's nice, isn't it?
面试怎么样啊
So how'd the interview go?
和学校的课程时间都有冲突
Oh, nothing's working out with the school times at the minute.
所以我找了几家中介机构把我的名字放在等候名单里
So I went to, erm, some of the agencies and put my name down on the waiting list,
我早上可以去做保洁
cos I could do cleaning in the morning.
找了几家酒店 还有咖啡厅
Went to some hotels. Went round all the cafes.
腿都快走断了
Must have walked for bloody miles.
在我开始工作前
Well, I can pick the kids up for you, you know.
可以帮你接孩子
Till I start work again.
丹 答案是椰子
Dan. The answer is "coconuts".
回答正确
Correct.
怎么突然说起椰子了
What's he talking about, "coconuts"?
告诉妈妈
Ah, shall we tell your mum?
- 说吧  - 我在楼梯上拍球的时候
- Go on.  - When I was bouncing my ball on the stairs.
- 什么楼梯  - 我们家的楼梯
- What stairs?  - The stairs in our house.
- 对  - 丹问了我一个问题
- Yeah.  - Dan asked me a question.
什么问题
What, what question did he ask ya?
鲨鱼和椰子
"What kills people more?
- 哪一个杀人更多  - 嗯
- "Coconuts or sharks?"  - Mmm-hmm.
我说是椰子
And I said coconuts.
你答对了吗
And you got it right?
- 是这样吗  - 他答对了
- Is that right?  - Yeah, he's right.
那是莫莉的照片吗
Is that Molly?
对 是莫莉
Yeah. Yeah, that's Molly, yeah.
拿过来看看 黛西
Let's see that, Dais.
给我看看那张
Show me that one.
莫莉 我喜欢这个名字
"Molly." Like the name.
她是什么样的人
What was she like?
她很特别
She was special.
她真的很特别 黛西
Yeah, she was special, Daisy.
不是温柔的类型
Not easy.
情绪就像过山车
She was up one minute, down the next.
聪明 幽默
Smart and funny. Huh.
我经常被她逗得哈哈大笑
Ah, that lass made me laugh.
她很善良
Kind.
心胸宽广
She had a big, big heart.
但是
But...
她说她的脑中就像一片汪洋
She said her head was like the ocean.
时而寂静 时而狂啸
Dead still, then wild.
不知自己将漂向何处
Never knew where she'd end up next.
听音乐缓解了她的病情
I mean, the music helped that.
但她最终还是撞上了礁石
But then she'd hit the rocks.
“今晚小船将驶向何处 丹”
"Where'll we sail to tonight, Dan?"
这是我们之间的小笑话
That was our little joke.
她的遗言是
Her last words to me were,
“我想要迎着狂风 扬帆远航”
"I wanna sail away, Dan, with the wind at me back.
“这样我就满足了 丹”
"That's all I need, Dan."
你们有孩子吗
Do you have any children?
我很想要孩子 但事与愿违
I'd have loved that, Daisy. No.
- 你想她吗  - 黛西
- Do you miss her?  - Dais.
没关系的
It's okay.
她有精神疾病
She was crazy.
照料她很累
Hard work.
但我还是全心全意地爱她
But I loved her to bits.
她走了 我的生活也迷失了
I'm lost without her, really.
- 喝点茶吧  - 哦 谢谢
- There you go, pet.  - Oh, thank you.
一定很辛苦吧
That must have been hard for you, Dan.
她生前是你一直在照顾她吗
I mean, did you look after her right till the end?
我以为她的去世对我是个解脱
Well, you know, I thought it'd be a relief when she passed away.
因为她的病 耽误了很多工作
Cos it was difficult to go into work, you know, when she was ill.
但我照顾了她那么长时间
And after you've been looking after somebody for so long...
她似乎已占据我全部的生活
It seems to take over your life, you know.
- 是啊 你会忘记自己的生活  - 嗯
- Yeah, and you forget your own.  - Huh.
身边有你 她很幸运
Well she was lucky to have you.
我以为黛西的爸爸是真命天子
Daisy's dad, I thought was something really special.
但他并不是
He turned out not to be.
我当时只有十八岁 没有听从妈妈的劝阻
Me mum tried to warn me about it, but I was 18, so I didn't listen.
在迪伦的爸爸身上又重蹈覆辙
And then I did the same thing with Dylan's dad.
你很年轻 人生还长着呢
You're a young lass, you got your whole life ahead of you.
等你重回校园 就是一片新的天地
And when you get back to those books, you'll be flying.
我现在看不了书 一看书就心烦
Yeah, I can't look at 'em, Dan. They really upset me.
- 你要坚持下去  - 嗯
- You gotta keep a hold, you know.  - Mmm-hmm.
孩子们都为你骄傲
You're doing your kids proud.
前进总需要风的动力
I mean, we all need the wind at our back every now and then.
- 不是吗  - 是啊
- Don't we?  - Mmm. Yeah.
这不达标啊 布莱克先生
Well that's not good enough, Mr Blake.
我怎么确定你联系过这些雇主呢
And how do I know you've actually been in contact with all these employers?
我走街串巷 亲手递的简历
Well, I walked round the town. I gave out me CV by hand.
证明在哪
Well, prove it.
- 这怎么证明  - 有收据吗
- How?  - Well, did you get a receipt?
用手机拍照了吗
Take a picture with your mobile?
用这个吗
With this?
我用人格担保
I give you my word that's what I did.
这样不达标啊 布莱克先生
That's not good enough, Mr Blake.
你在求职网站找工作了吗
What about the Universal Job Match online?
我去了图书馆 这是我的预约卡
I went to the library, there's my appointment card.
我脑门子都快爆了 已经尽全力了
Did my head in. And I tried my best.
还是不达标
It's not good enough.
能看一下您的简历吗
Can I look at your CV?
行
All right.
您在培训班什么也没学到吗
Did you not learn anything at the CV workshop?
我还真学了不少
You'd be surprised.
还是不达标吗 希拉
Not good enough, Sheila?
我要把你的情况
I'm afraid I'm gonna have to refer you
反映给决策者 并可能对你进行为期四周的处罚
to a decision maker for a possible sanction for four weeks.
你的收入将被冻结
Your payment will be frozen.
您可以申请特困补贴
You may be entitled to Hardship Allowance if you apply.
您明白吗
Do you understand?
处罚期间 您必须继续找工作
And if you are sanctioned, you must continue to look for work and sign on.
如不遵守 将再次受到处罚
If you don't, you may be sanctioned again.
两次或以上的制裁期限可达十三周
And it's likely to be for thirteen weeks on the second occasion, and thereafter.
上限可达三年
And likely to be the maximum of up to three years.
需要我给你写去食品救助站的介绍信吗
Would you like me to write you a referral to a food bank?
丹 你不会要搬走了吧
Dan, you're not leaving, are you?
我要去巴哈马度假了
Aye, I'm off to the Bahamas.
就是看腻了这些老家具 换换口味
Nah, I'm just sick of the old stuff. I need a change.
你没事吧 丹
Are you okay, Dan?
我没事
I'm fine, son.
你脸色不太好
You don't look okay.
我没事 真的
No, really, I'm fine.
你最近都不催我们倒垃圾了
You haven't given us a row about leaving the rubbish out.
我没事 老中 真的
I'm okay, China, really.
需要帮忙就告诉我 丹
If you need anything, Dan, let me know.
啥事都行
Absolutely anything.
我说真的 有事就说话
I mean it, Dan, anything.
知道了 孩子
I know, son.
二十 四十 六十 八十 一百
Twenty, forty, sixty, eighty, a hundred.
Twenty, forty, sixty, eighty, two hundred.
行吗
All right?
好 二百镑可以了
Aye, fair enough.
还有什么要卖的吗
Anything else I can help you with?
没有了
No, that's it.
这些工具呢
What about these?
质量不错
Good quality hand tools.
绝对不卖 我很快就要回去工作了
Nae chance. I'll be ganning back to work soon enough.
要是想卖了就找我
Well, the offer's there.
这个挺好看的 怎么卖
Now these look nice. How much d'you want?
这个不卖
They're not for sale, mate.
改变主意了就给我打电话 再见
Give us a ring if you change your mind. See you now.
宝贝 你怎么了
What are you doing?
哎呀 你都冻坏了
Oh, you're freezing.
出什么事了
What's wrong?
今天学校里的女同学都在笑我
Well, erm, the girls at school are making fun of me.
什么
They're what?
学校里的女同学都在笑我
The girls at school are making fun of me.
她们为什么笑你
Why are they making fun of you?
我的鞋底掉了
My shoes fell apart.
是吗
Oh, did they?
不是用胶水粘过了吗
But we glued them back together.
- 嗯  - 又掉了？
- Mmm.  - They fell apart again?
给你买双新鞋吧
All right, we can get you a new pair of shoes.
可我们没有钱
We don't have the money.
钱你不用操心 我会给你买新鞋的
Don't you worry about that, we can get you a new pair of shoes.
好
Okay.
有个女同学听说食品救济处的事了
One of the girls heard about what happened at the food bank.
她们说闲话了 对吗
And they're saying things to you about that, are they?
我会解决的 你别担心
We'll get it sorted, don't you worry.
想跟我一起睡吗
D'you wanna sleep here with me?
躺过来宝贝 把被子掖好
Yeah? All right, babe, roll over then. Tuck in.
躺过来 我给你掖被子
That's it. Roll right over. I'll tuck you in.
乖孩子
Good girl.
喂
Hello?
喂 是埃文吗
Hello, is that Ivan?
我是 请问是哪位
It is, yeah. Who's that?
我是凯蒂 超市里见过
It's, it's Katie, the girl at the supermarket.
你给了我电话号码
You gave me... You gave me your phone number.
哦 我记得你
Okay, I remember you.
我是想问问你说的那份工作
Yeah, I was, erm... I was ringing about the work that you were talking about.
很高兴认识你
It's nice to meet you.
在我面前不用紧张 我知道你心里很煎熬
You don't need to be nervous with me. I can see you're in pain.
不用这样 好吗
You don't... You don't need to be, all right?
我会帮你的
I'm gonna help you. Okay?
不要哭
So, don't cry, right.
我不会让你哭的 会帮你渡过难关
I don't want you to cry, I'm gonna help you.
你的情况我知道 埃文跟我说了
I know the situation. Ivan's told us a little bit about you and, you know,
我就是来帮助你的
and that's what I'm here for. I am gonna help you.
嗨
Hey, ya.
- 都好吗  - 好啊
- All right?  - Yeah.
孩子们都睡了吧
Did they, er, they go down all right?
好哄的很 倒头就睡 你那怎么样
Nae bother. Both fast asleep. How'd it go?
挺好的 去参加了一个单亲互助会
Yeah, it was good, it was good. It was a, it was a single-parent meeting.
跟一个单亲妈妈聊了会 她人很好
One of the mums came and spoke to me afterwards, she was really nice.
还是好人多啊
Ah, there's some good people round, yeah.
是啊
Yeah.
你要好好照顾自己啊 丹
Make sure you take care of yourself, Dan, won't ya?
- 当然  - 好
- Course I will.  - All right.
- 回见了  - 晚安
- See you soon.  - Good night.
- 早上替我亲亲孩子们  - 会的
- Give my love to the kids in the morning.  - I will do.
- 谢谢  - 晚安
- Thank you.  - 'Night.
丹 是我 谢谢你今晚过来帮我
Dan, it's me. Erm, thank you for coming round tonight.
黛西醒了 她忘记问你作业的事了
Daisy woke up and she forgot to ask you about her school project.
她要采访一个人 了解他的职业
She's, erm, she's gotta interview somebody about their work
她想要采访你
and she wants to speak to you.
孩子们都很喜欢你讲的故事
Oh, and they, they loved all your stories.
她说迪伦一直笑个不停
She said that Dylan was just laughing and laughing.
太温馨了 她说的时候我差点哭了
It was lovely. Nearly made me cry when she told me.
好吧 回头见 睡个好觉 晚安
All right, I'll speak to you soon. Sleep well. 'Night.
我约了姑娘
I've come to see the girl.
好 进来
Okay. Come in.
钱是付给你吗
Erm, do I pay you?
付给姑娘就行 就是那间
No, you pay the girl. It's that door there.
好
Right.
噢 不 丹
Oh, no, Dan.
凯蒂 你没有必要做这个
Katie, you don't need to do this.
我不想让你看到我这个样子
You shouldn't see me like this.
对不起
I'm sorry.
你触碰了我的底线 出去
No, this, this is cut off. This is separate. Can you... You need to get out.
在家里我说不出口 但在这里我必须要说
Listen, I couldn't speak to you in the flat, I need to speak to you now.
丹 求你了 出去
Dan, please, get out.
凯蒂 我要跟你谈谈
Oh, Katie, please, I need to speak to you.
我只是想跟你谈谈 凯蒂
I just wanna speak to you. Katie!
丹 求你了 你走吧
Dan, please, just go.
丹 我不想看见你 你走吧
Dan, please, I don't want you here! Will you just go, please!
- 我给你做了一个书架  - 什么？
- I've built you a bookcase.  - What?
给你放书的
For your books.
哦 丹 求你了 快走吧
Oh, Dan. Please, just go.
- 求你快走 我不想在这看见你  - 我的心都要碎了
- Please, just go, I don't want you here.  - This is breaking my heart.
丹 求你了别管我
Dan, please, just leave me alone.
我已经挣了三百镑
I've got 300 quid in my pocket.
孩子们能吃上新鲜水果了
I can buy the kids fresh fruit.
你要是无法接受 我也不想再见你了
If you can't deal with it, I can't see you any more.
我必须回去工作 你明白吗
Listen, I've gotta go back inside. D'you understand?
我不想再跟你说话了
I don't wanna speak to you any more.
不要再关心我了
And don't show me any more love.
这会让我崩溃的 丹
Cos you're gonna break me, Dan.
我不明白
I don't understand.
你申请过什么工作
So what jobs have you actually applied for?
这就是一场无休止的闹剧
It's a monumental farce, isn't it?
你坐在那 胸前佩戴着友好的名牌“安”
You sitting there with your friendly name tag on your chest, Ann,
对面坐着个病重的老头 申请着并不存在的工作
opposite a sick man looking for nonexistent jobs,
就算成功也无法上岗
that I can't take anyway.
浪费着我的时间 你的时间 雇主的时间
Wasting my time, employers' time, your time.
而这一切只是在羞辱我 折磨我
And all it does is humiliate me, grind me down.
或许这就是你们的意图 把我的名字从电脑上抹去
Or is that the point, to get my name off those computers?
我不玩了
Well, I'm not doing it any more.
我受够了
I've had enough.
麻烦帮我预约
I want my date for my appointment
就业支持津贴申诉面谈
for my appeal for Employment and Support.
- 你还没预约上面谈吗  - 没有
- Have you not had that yet?  - No.
听我一句劝 丹
Please listen to me, Dan.
你目前没有任何收入 停止申请失业津贴的风险太大
It's a huge decision to come off JSA without any other income coming in.
申诉过程可能要花好几周
Look, it... It could be weeks before your appeal comes through.
强制性再评估的周期没有上限
You see, there's no time limit for a mandatory reconsideration.
我的时间是有上限的
I've got a time limit.
可能申诉还会不成功
And you might not win.
还是继续申请失业津贴吧
Please, just keep signing on.
找个人帮你在网上求职
Get somebody to help you with the online job searches.
否则 你有可能失去一切
Otherwise, you could lose everything.
请不要贸然行事 我就见过类似的情况
Please don't do this. I've seen it before.
好人 诚实的人 最后无家可归
Good people, honest people, on the street.
谢谢你的建议 安
Thank you, Ann.
但失去自尊就等于失去了一切
But when you lose your self-respect, you're done for.
哥几个回头见啦
I'll be seeing you gentlemen later.
等保安来看看这个吧
Oh, wait until security sees this.
喂 你这闹什么幺蛾子呢
What's going on here? What are you fucking playing at?
- 哎 别碰我们  - 你倒挺机智
- Aye-aye. You cannot touch us.  - Well that's clever, in't it?
这是我新创作的装置艺术
It's me new art installation.
当然可以 小伙子 来吧
Eh? Certainly can, lads. Come on.
嚯 你们这新潮玩意倒是齐活
Look at this, you got all the technology.
- 看呀  - 真不敢相信
- Look at this!  - I can't believe it.
真不敢相信 看你干的好事
I cannot believe it, man. What have you done?
这是我的新嗜好 要不也写进简历
This is me new hobby. Shall I put that on my CV?
你就从来没有想过
Did you stop, even for a second,
这样做可能造成的后果吗
to think about the consequences of what you've done here?
我只知道 如果约不到面谈
All I know, mate, is if I divvent get my appeal date,
我就每天上这搞创作
I'll be here every day doing this.
- 太离谱了 还每天  - 对 每天
- Unbelievable. Every day?  - Every day.
本 干脆报警吧
Tell you what, Ben, just phone the police. Okay.
真不敢相信
I cannae... Listen, mate, I cannot believe this now.
这事我们不管了 只能报警了
This is out of our hands. We're gonna have to phone the cops, man.
如果你能称职一点
Well, if youse had done your job like you should have done,
我也不会出此下策
I wouldn't have had to resort to this.
真不敢相信 真不敢相信
I cannot believe it. I cannot believe it.
去 帮他一把
Go on, lad, give him a hand.
好
Yes!
至理名言啊
Words of wisdom!
好样哒 小兄弟
You're the man, wee man! Eh?
我操 很赞
Fucking eh? Yeah!
人间精品
Are youse out of work, mate?
你他妈就是丹尼尔·布莱克？
Are you fucking... Are you Daniel Blake?
就是在下
I am Daniel Blake, yes.
隆重介绍丹尼尔·布莱克
Hey, this is Daniel Blake!
此真壮举哉 耶
Fucking look at that. Yeah!
耶 嘿
Yeah! Hey!
哎呀你都冻坏了 穿我的外套吧
You look fucking freezing, pal. Here, have my jacket.
- 没事  - 快 外套穿上
- No, no.  - No, come on, man, have my fucking jacket.
没事 好好照顾自己
It's all right, son. Look after yoursel', eh?
注意保暖
Keep yoursel' warm like.
真是位绅士啊
You're a gentleman.
你要申诉的是什么事
So what's, what's your appeal all about?
骗子
Liar!
你因涉嫌损坏公物被捕
You're... You're under arrest on suspicion of criminal damage.
这是正义的失败
Hey, a miscarriage of justice, eh.
慢着 你退后
Slow down. Whoa. Back off.
好吧
All right, all right, all right.
你他妈抓他干什么
What the fuck's going on? Eh?
怎么不抓那些尽知道处罚别人的混蛋
You should be arresting the wankers who came up with sanctions. Eh?
那个红脸蛋的死秃子 叫啥来着
That preachy baldy cunt. What's his name?
那个叫什么伊恩·邓肯的混蛋
Ian Duncan fucking what's-his-face.
还有那些住大别墅的土豪
Aye, and the posh dicks in their mansions
搞出了“卧室税”这么个玩意折腾残疾人
who came up with the fucking bedroom tax for disabled...
走吧 反正你们警察也干不长了
Listen, youse are all gonna be out of a fucking job anyway.
要被私有化了吧 傻缺保守党
Privatizing you, eh? All the fucking Tories, man.
那些首富俱乐部成员
Aye, members of the fucking big club, eh.
伊顿公学的兔崽子们
Fucking posh Eton twats.
应该给丹尼尔·布莱克封爵
Sir Daniel fucking Blake, pal!
应该给你建座雕像
Hey, should be a statue made for you, pal.
丹尼尔·布莱克爵士
Fucking Sir Daniel Blake!
国民表率 社会栋梁
Yer a fucking beauty!
耶
Yay!
现在怎么办
So, what happens now?
这是一份警告单的复印件
Right, this is a copy of the caution sheet.
因为你已经供认了全部罪名
Because you fully admitted the offences
且无犯罪记录
and you've been of good character in the past,
根据《公共秩序法》第五章
we're cautioning you for the offence of criminal damage,
对你损害公物的行为提出警告
under Section Five of the Public Order Act.
请切记 如若再犯
But please remember that these can come back
这些记录将对你不利
and haunt you if you re-offend.
所以 不要给自己惹麻烦
So try to keep yourself out of trouble.
好吧
Aye.
- 送他出去吧  - 这边走 先生
- See him out, please.  - This way, Mr Blake.
丹 丹
Dan. Dan!
出来 我要跟你说话
Come, I need to talk to you.
我们打电话你都不接
We called you loads of times.
丹
Dan!
妈妈最近很伤心
Mum's been so sad lately.
你为什么不跟她说话了
Why don't you speak to her?
你电话欠费了吗
Don't you have credit on the phone?
我看见你了
I see you.
我们知道你心脏不好
We understand what happened to your heart.
妈妈问过你的邻居了
Mum spoke to one of your neighbours.
我们之前不知道
We didn't know about it.
外面好冷啊
It's cold out here.
我冻死了
I'm freezing.
黛西 我身体不太舒服
Please, Daisy, I'm not feeling very well.
我给你做了点古斯米饭
I made you some couscous.
还带了迪伦的棒棒糖
And Dylan sent you his lollipop.
他也很想你呢
He's really missing you, too.
黛西 你还是走吧 求你了
Just go, Daisy, please.
我能问你个问题吗 丹
Can I ask you one question, Dan?
你是不是帮过我们
Did you help us?
应该是吧
Suppose so.
那我们为什么不能帮你呢
So why can't I help you?
对不起
I'm sorry.
对不起 黛西
I'm sorry, Daisy.
真的对不起
I'm really sorry.
我不是个容易紧张的人 凯蒂 但这次我真的紧张了
You know, I'm not usually a nervous person, Katie, but I'm nervous about this.
这是人之常情 丹
It's only natural, Dan.
我就是想有个了结
I just want it done, you know?
你准备很充分 文件都备齐了
Yeah. Well, you're prepared. You got all your papers.
代理人也很棒
You've got a good, good person representing you.
等结束了 就来我们家吃晚饭庆祝
And then when you're done, you can come, come to dinner to celebrate.
孩子们都很想见你呢
The kids are really looking forward to seeing you.
你好 我是丹尼尔·布莱克 我是来申诉的
Hi, er, Daniel Blake. I've come for my appeal for the reinstatement of my...
想重新申请就业支持津贴
Employment and Support Allowance.
- 你好 丹尼尔  - 你好
- Daniel, hi. Hello. Are you all right?  - Hello.
- 我是凯蒂 丹尼尔的朋友  - 你好
- Hi, I'm Katie. I'm a friend of Daniel's.  - Hi.
- 你是来支持他的吗  - 是
- You're here for support, yeah?  - Yeah.
丹尼尔 你的申诉将由具备法定资格的委员会主席和医生评估
Daniel, your appeal will be heard by a legally qualified chairperson and a doctor.
- 希望能有好运气吧  - 嗯
- Aye, fingers crossed.  - Yeah...
我要是申诉失败 就露宿街头了
If I lose this appeal, I'm out on the streets.
你的医生发来了健康报告
Well, we've got some updated reports here from your GP,
你的个人健康顾问和理疗师
your own consultant and your physiotherapist.
他们都对结果非常气愤
And they're all furious.
你一定会成功的
You're gonna win this, Dan.
这种申诉我每周都会处理
I do this every week.
- 我以性命担保  - 我说吧
- I bet me life on it.  - I told ya.
别紧张 自然地回答问题就好
Just be yourself, answer the questions and relax.
我真的很有信心
I'm really confident.
你有什么问题吗
D'you have any questions?
我的确有几件事不吐不快啊
Well, I've got one or two things I'd like to get off me chest.
- 他们会听吗  - 这是他们的职责
- But will they listen?  - It's the least they can do.
我能跟他一起进去吗
And can I go in with him?
我帮你问问 你想她陪你进去吗
I'll certainly ask. Would you like her to?
- 当然好  - 好吗
- Yeah. Definitely, yeah.  - Yeah?
好 我会问的 完全没问题
Okay, I'll certainly ask. No problem at all.
好的 谢谢
All right. Thank you.
乐意帮助 我先去看看情况
My pleasure. I'll just go and see what the score is.
- 好  - 听上去不错 对吧
- Yeah.  - Sounds good, don't it?
你看那帮人
Look at them.
真有意思 我的身家性命全掌握在他们手上
It's funny, they've got my life in their hands.
凯蒂 谢谢你陪我来
Thanks, Katie, for coming.
谢谢你让我来
Thank you for asking me.
你这个固执的老混蛋
You stubborn old bastard.
我想去洗把脸
I think I'll go and freshen up, yeah?
好
All right.
这里谁快打电话叫救护车 拨九九九
Can somebody, er, phone an ambulance, please? 9-9-9.
有人在厕所里晕倒了
There's a guy collapsed in the toilet. He's flat out.
快打九九九 快
Phone 9-9-9. Somebody, please.
丹
Dan!
不 丹
No! Dan!
他心脏病发作了 做人工呼吸吧
Just had a heart attack. Yeah, two breaths, please.
哦 丹
Oh, Dan!
- 人工呼吸…  - 他还有呼吸吗
- Just the two breaths...  - Is he breathing?
哦 丹
Oh, Dan.
我们已经尽力救他了
Listen, we're trying to help him as much as we can.
继续啊 继续啊 不要停
No, no, no, please keep going, please keep going. Don't stop.
他已经去了
I'm afraid we've lost him.
不 别说这种话 不要说这种话
No, don't say that, please don't say that. No.
- 不  - 真的很遗憾
- No, please!  - I'm so sorry.
请节哀
I'm sorry.
- 求你了  - 救护车呢
- Please...  - Where's the ambulance now?
- 求你了  - 病人没有回应
- Please.  - No response at all.
求你们不要放弃
Please. Please try again.
嗯…
Erm...
他们管这个叫“贫民葬礼” 因为早上九点是最便宜的时段
They call this a "pauper's funeral" because it's the cheapest slot, at 9:00.
但对我们来说 丹绝不是贫民
But Dan wasn't a pauper to us.
他给我们的关爱 千金难买
He gave us things that money can't buy.
他去世后 我从他身上找到了这封信
When he died, I found this on him.
他习惯用铅笔写字
He always used to write in pencil.
嗯…
Erm...
他本想在申诉时读的 但再也没有机会了
And he wanted to read it at his appeal but he never got the chance to.
他是个满腔热情的人
And I swear that this lovely man,
本有大把机会回馈和奉献
had so much more to give,
是政府让他过早地离开了我们
and that the State drove him to an early grave.
他是这么写的
And this is what he wrote.
“我不是客户 不是顾客 也不是服务用户”
"I am not a client, a customer, nor a service user.
“我不是懒人 不是小偷 更不是乞丐窃贼”
"I am not a shirker, a scrounger, a beggar, nor a thief.
“我不是一串社保号码 不是屏幕上的一段数据”
"I'm not a National Insurance Number or blip on a screen.
“我按时纳税 一分不少 我为此深感自豪”
"I paid my dues, never a penny short, and proud to do so.
“我不向权贵卑躬屈膝 诚心对待邻里 尽我所能伸出援助之手”
"I don't tug the forelock, but look my neighbour in the eye and help him if I can.
“我不接受 更不寻求施舍”
"I don't accept or seek charity.
“我的名字 是丹尼尔·布莱克 我是堂堂正正的人 不是街边乞怜的狗”
"My name is Daniel Blake. I am a man, not a dog.
“我在此讨回本属于我的权利”
"As such, I demand my rights.
“并要求你们以尊重之心待我”
"I demand you treat me with respect.
“我 丹尼尔·布莱克 是一个公民”
"I, Daniel Blake, am a citizen,
“无所奢求 无可妥协”
"nothing more and nothing less."
谢谢
Thank you.